Hey, בוקר טוב. boker tov. So, this last פרק perek we've been
dealing or two פרקים prakim with the parts of the תורה Torah
which are the father annulling for the daughter and then particularly that
very very quickly moved into the or didn't even stay there started
dealt with the like more ambiguous or interesting case of the נערה
מאורסה na'arah me'orasah that was under both the control of the father
and the groom and then a lot about the husband annulling for
his wife and now we move to in getting like about two
פרקים prakim or three or whatever from the end here three דפים
dapim from the end we move at the very end to the
case in the תורה Torah which seems to be straightforward ונדר אלמנה
וגרושה v'neder almanah u'grushah כל אשר kol asher what was it כל
אשר אסרה על נפשה יקום עליה kol asher asrah al nafshah yakum
aleha which is if a woman is a divorcee or a widow
and there's no man in her life not a father or a
husband I mean there might be a father but it's irrelevant now
she's emancipated even if she's a minor then her vows are binding
there's nobody to annul it. So that's what the משנה mishnah picks
up with and interestingly the משנה mishnah begins with a פסוק. pasuk.
Okay so let's take a look. ונדר אלמנה
וגרושה v'neder almanah u'grushah it had some ellipsis here יקום עליה yakum
aleha כל אשר אסרה על נפשה יקום עליה. kol asher asrah al
nafshah yakum aleha. כיצד keitzad how's this? Now what do you mean
how's this? She makes the vow nobody annuls it. So the point
is is that it's asking implicitly which is why do I need
the פסוק pasuk what do I need what do I need the
פסוק pasuk to tell me? I mean obviously there's nobody to annul
her vows what's the point of the פסוק? pasuk? So here's what
the פסוק pasuk is telling me. אמרה amrah if a woman says
הריני נזירה לאחר שלושים יום hareini nezirah achar shloshim yom I will
be a נזיר nazir after 30 days. Okay אף על פי שניסת
בתוך שלושים יום אינו יכול להפר. af al pi shenisset b'toch shloshim
yom eino yachol l'hafer. Now she is at this stage single she's
a בוגרת bogeret so she's not under her father's control or she's
an אלמנה almanah or גרושה grushah she makes this vow when there
is nobody to annul it and then she gets married and then
it takes effect when she's already married. So here's the question does
the husband's rights to annul the vow go when the vow is
based on when the vow is made or based on when the
vow takes effect? So the משנה mishnah assumes we'll see in the
גמרא gemara it's a מחלוקת תנאים machloket tanna'im the משנה mishnah assumes
that the husband's rights focuses on when the vow is made and
therefore what it's saying is the חידוש chiddush of the תורה Torah
that a vow made by an אלמנה almanah or גרושה grushah
is established cannot be annulled the חידוש chiddush is that if she
made it when she was an אלמנה almanah or גרושה grushah or
like I said a בוגרת bogeret any woman not under the control
of a man then it remains then it is not able to
be annulled even if it only took effect when she was already
married. Okay so אף על פי שניסת תוך שלושים יום אינו יכול
להפר af al pi shenisset b'toch shloshim yom eino yachol l'hafer he
cannot annul it. Now the same would be true in the
reverse. Okay נדרה והיא ברשות הבעל nadrah v'hi b'reshut habaal she made
a vow whilst she was married מיפר לה mefer lah he will
be able to annul it even if meaning obviously but it means
even if the effect of the vow takes place should have taken
place after their marriage. כיצד keitzad what would be the case? אמרה
הריני נזירה לאחר שלושים יום amrah hareini nezirah achar shloshim yom I
will be a נזיר nazir starting after 30 days. So it only
will take effect after 30 days. אף על פי שנתאלמנה או נתגרשה
בתוך שלושים יום af al pi shenit'almanah o nitgarshah b'toch shloshim yom
she is widowed or divorced within 30 days before it took effect
הרי זה מופר harei zeh mufer it is annulled. Now he can't
annul it after she's widowed or divorced especially after she's widowed that
would be a good trick but the point is he annuls it
and then he dies or then he divorces her. So the time
it should have taken effect was after was a period in which
he was no longer had the rights to say anything about the
vow. It does not matter because the power to annul or the
or the inability to annul whatever is all determined by the time
the vow was taken. If at that time she was not under
the control of any man then it then nobody can annul it
regardless of when it takes effect and if at that time she
was married to her husband then the husband can annul it also
regardless of when it takes effect.
נדרה בו ביום ונתגרשה בו ביום והחזירה בו ביום nadrah bo bayom
v'nitgarshah bo bayom v'hechezirah bo bayom so it's a very busy day.
Exactly. So she took a vow her husband divorced her then he
remarried her. Okay. So here's the thing and it's all the same
day. So can he still annul? Because it was a vow that
was made under while he was married to her while she was
under his control and it's the same day that he heard and
now that he's coming to do to do the act of annulling
she's also under his control. So would that work? So the הלכה
halachah is אינו יכול להפר eino yachol l'hafer he cannot annul it.
זה הכלל zeh haklal this is the rule. כל שיצאה לרשות עצמה
שעה אחת אינו יכול להפר. kol sheyatzah l'reshut atzmah sha'ah achat eino
yachol l'hafer. Once she gains her own independence for even one moment
he loses the right to be מיפר mefer and that could be
understood as also part of the חידוש chiddush of the תורה Torah
ונדר אלמנה וגרושה. v'neder almanah u'grushah. Once she is enters into a
state of אלמנה וגרושה almanah u'grushah once she reaches a state of
independence then. And you do not get to sort of ignore that
state and say, oh well, let's look at it as just she
was continuously married the whole time. Okay, no, she got that independence
and that moment that she became divorced, right, the vow became binding,
and he can no longer be מפר maifer afterwards. It's also based
on the principle that a בעל ba’al is not מפר maifer בקודמים.
bikodmim. Can't be מפר maifer things that preceded him. And the second
marriage is not looked at as a continuation of the first. Like
for example, if he was a כהן, Kohen, he wouldn't get to
say, oh, let me remarry her and we'll just look at it
as a continuation of the first. Right? It's not looked at as
a continuation. It is a second marriage. And from the perspective of
that second marriage, this vow predated that second marriage. So he cannot
annul it during that time. Okay? And so that also, that divorce
and that being independent breaks up any sense of, you know, continuous
state. It is not a continuous state and now he cannot annul
it. Yes?
Possibly you could also look at this perhaps as a kind of
a קיום kiyum when he divorces her.
The act of divorcing, a
kind of a way of giving her her independence.
Possibly. I mean, right. I mean, you know, you mean even if
it's not motivated by the vow, the fact that it results in
giving her her independence, that's an interesting thought. Okay, so now it
says like this. תניא, Tanya, turn to a ברייתא. Baraita. אלמנה וגרושה
שאמרה, Almana u’grusha she’amra, הריני נזירה לכשאנשא. hareini nezira l’cheshe’inasei. I will
be a נזירה nezira when I get married.
ונישאת, Veniset, and she got married. Similar to the משנה Mishna but
not identical.
רבי ישמעאל אומר Rabbi Yishmael omer יפר, yafer, he can annul. It
doesn't matter that the vow was made before the marriage, since it
took effect during the marriage, it's a vow that he can annul.
It goes when it takes effect. רבי עקיבא אומר,
Rabbi
Akiva
omer, yeah, but
the קיום kiyum and the marriage are simultaneous, like it's not afterwards,
right? Like the same second.
Fine.
So, but it's during the marriage. It doesn't matter that it wasn't
after, it just wasn't before.
Well, but when did he find out? Because the moment he gets
married, she's already a נזירה. nezira.
Yeah, but he has a day to annul it. He has a
day to annul it. Presumably the day would start from the time
he becomes empowered to do so. It would be the day that
he got married.
רבי עקיבא אומר Rabbi Akiva omer לא יפר, lo yafer, he cannot
be מפר. maifer. Now, וסימנא יללי. vesimana yelali. Now,
רש"י Rashi says it. Okay, but I didn't see it in the
רש"י. Rashi. The ר"ן Ran doesn't explain what that means, but I
figured it out, which is we're going to have in this little
piece, it says יפר yafer and לא יפר, lo yafer, right? רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael is the one who says יפר, yafer, רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva is the one who says לא יפר. lo yafer. They're
going to reverse their positions in the next case. So it's going
to be לא יפר, lo yafer, יפר. yafer. Okay, so יפר לא
יפר, לא יפר יפר. yafer lo yafer, lo yafer yafer. Okay, but
you have to remember what the cases are and who's speaking. So
I don't know how much the סימן siman helps you. Anyway, okay,
so that's case number one. But רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says the
husband's power goes when it takes effect and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says when it's been made. אשת איש שאמרה, Eshes ish she’amra, now
here's the reverse case. She's already married and she says, הריני נזירה
לכשאגרש. hareini nezira l’cheshe’etgaresh.
I will be a נזירה nezira once I get divorced.
ונתגרשה, Venisgaresh, and the husband says here, let me help you with
that, and he divorces her. Okay, so she's divorced. רבי ישמעאל אומר
Rabbi Yishmael omer לא יפר. lo yafer. So רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael,
who again focuses on when it takes effect, says, well, it took
effect when she was divorced, so any annulment was meaningless. The annulment
relates to the period when it takes effect, and at that moment
she's no longer married to him. ורבי עקיבא אומר VeRabbi Akiva omer
יפר. yafer. And רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says he can, because if
he annulled it on the day she made it, it doesn't matter
that it only took effect later on.
Okay, it all goes by the time she made the vow. אמר
רבי ישמעאל, Amar Rabbi Yishmael, one minute, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael said,
הרי אומר, harei omer, the verse says, ונדר אלמנה וגרושה כל אשר
אסרה על נפשה יקום עליה. veneder almana u’grusha kol asher asra al
nafsha yakum aleha. So it says אשר אסרה על נפשה, asher asra
al nafsha, makes forbidden. So the focus is what state is she
in when it becomes forbidden, okay, and we focus on when it
becomes forbidden. We focus on the effect of the vow. עד שהיא
נדר בשעת אלמנות וגירושין. ad she-hi neder besha’at almanut ve’gerushin.
It focuses on the question of whether the vow is in effect
when she's an אלמנה וגרושה, almana u’grusha, when she's independent, or is
it in effect when she's married. It says אשר אסרה על נפשה.
asher asra al nafsha. Okay,
so I'm sorry, actually אסרה על נפשה asra al nafsha is what
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is going to be focusing on. It says,
actually, his point is ונדר. veneder. ונדר veneder meaning not the act
of taking the vow but the actual reality of the vow itself.
That's the דרשה. drasha. ונדר veneder goes by אלמנה וגרושה. almana u’grusha.
When you have the reality of the vow, then we look, are
you independent or are you married? It focuses on when the reality
of the vow exists. רבי עקיבא סבר, Rabbi Akiva savar, הרי אומר,
harei omer, and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would say back, it says
כל אשר אסרה על נפשה, kol asher asra al nafsha, and anything
that she made forbidden. So that's focused not on the reality of
the vow, of the vow being in existence and taking effect, but
on the act of taking the vow, אסרה על נפשה. asra al
nafsha. הרי אומר כל אשר אסרה על נפשה, harei omer kol asher
asra al nafsha, עד שאיסור נדר בשעת אלמנות וגירושין, ad she-isur neder
besha’at almanut ve’gerushin, which doesn't mean the effect of the prohibition but
it means the act of prohibiting takes effect, the act of making
the vow. That's what we look at. Was she an אלמנה וגרושה
almana u’grusha or was she not? Let's just say let's do one
more line and then take a question. אמר רב חסדא Amar Rav
Chisda but you know what let me pause here. Okay yes what
do you want to ask חנן?
Chanan? The משנה mishna רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva position is consistent with
the משנה. mishna.
Yes, well that's exactly what the גמרא's Gemara going to turn to.
It seems very clearly that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is the משנה
mishna and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael is an opposing view. Yes, and
now the גמרא's Gemara going to say exactly that or ask or
see if there's maybe a way to even not make it exactly
the משנה. mishna. אמר רב חסדא Amar Rav Chisda so says רב
חסדא Rav Chisda see this is exactly what חנן Chanan just said,
מתניתין רבי עקיבא היא. Matnitin Rabbi Akiva hi. Our משנה mishna is
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Our משנה mishna says you go about the
time the vow was made. אביי אמר אפילו תימא רבי ישמעאל. Abaye
amar afilu tema Rabbi Yishmael. אביי Abaye says it could even be
רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. מתניתין תליה נפשה ביומי. Matnitin talya nafsha beyomei.
The משנה mishna when she says it'll take effect, she doesn't say
after I get divorced or when I get married. She says based
on a certain number of days. It'll take effect after thirty days.
ברייתא, Baraita,
the ברייתא baraita here this debate we just had, תליה נפשה בניסויין
talya nafsha benissuin
makes it dependent on when I get married, when I get divorced.
Now why that should be different in half a minute but let's
just read the next few words. שלמו יומי Shalmu yomei now this
phrase I'm about to read really elaborates the תליה נפשה ביומי. talya
nafsha beyomei. Okay some actually say it, it belonged a little earlier.
So in the משנה mishna which is going by the days, thirty
days, שלמו יומי ולא נתגרשה שלמו יומי ולא מתנסבא. shalmu yomei velo
nitgarsha shalmu yomei velo mitnasba. So it would be possible in the
משנה mishna that the thirty days would run out and her status
wouldn't change. Right, so if she's married and she says I'll be
a נזירה nezira in thirty days, it's possible she'll be a נזירה
nezira when she is married. It just so happens by chance that
she got divorced. Or if she's independent and she says I'll be
a נזירה nezira in thirty days, it could have happened that it
would have taken effect by chance she got married. So there basically
the state of her being married or being divorced is that happens
is seen as sort of not intrinsic to the identity of the
vow. The vow basically, even רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, this is the
argument, that even רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael who says you go when
it takes effect, that's when by definition the period of it taking
effect is by definition a different status than when she is when
she took it. So when she takes it and says it'll take
effect when I get married, it'll take effect when I get divorced,
she's basically already intrinsic to the nature of the vow is the
act of taking the vow took place during one status and the
effect is being defined as taking place when she has a different
status. So when they are opposed like that, right, by definition act
during one status, effect during another status, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says
I go in favor of when it takes effect. But when it's
by chance that her status changed and in theory it all could
have been with the first status, then he says then it's identified
as a vow based on that original status, not on the second
status. Okay so that's a way of saying that by רבי ישמעאל,
Rabbi Yishmael, fascinating right way, we I don't think ever would have
occurred to us to have said, oh alright maybe we can get
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael to fit in, but when you say it
that way, yeah, that makes a certain amount of sense. Okay so...
right...
okay fine.
Fine. I mean the line that the ר"ן Ran says, if you
look like eight lines before the line gets wide, I mean right
before he says ולעניין הלכה uleinyan halacha he says כיון שבתחלתו היה
ראוי הנדר לחול באותו רשות שהיה בשעת אמירה. keivan shebitchilato haya raui
haneder lachul beoto reshut shehaya beshaat amira. Right, when you took it,
then it could have been that the effect would have been at
the same status of the act of taking. And therefore it was
just by chance they got broken up but that it all could
have happened in the same status. It's that original status that would
define even according to רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. And now the גמרא
Gemara just makes so that's the end of that סוגיא sugya we
would either way anyway פסקינן paskin like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva because
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is הלכה כרבי עקיבא מחבירו halacha kerabbi akiva
mechavero and it's our סתם משנה. stam mishna. Well whether it's our
סתם משנה stam mishna is dependent on this last point. And now
we just look at the final line of our משנה mishna that
says זה הכלל כל zeh haklal kol, שיצאה לרשות עצמה שעה אחת
אינו יכול להפר. Once she even gets for one moment in her
own control, he cannot be מפר. meifer. So the גמרא's Gemara going
to look at two זה הכללs. zeh haklal זה הכלל דקתני גבי
נערה המאורסה Zeh haklal diktani gabei naarah hameorasah back in כתובות. Ketubot.
Everybody remember כתובות? Ketubot? Back in כתובות, Ketubot, right, where it says
that it speaks about the act of חופה chuppah and the her
leaving the father's house and going to the husband's house or the
father putting handing her over to the messengers that have been sent
by the husband, etc. And it says this is the כלל. klal.
So we'll take a look. It'll say what the זה הכלל zeh
haklal is. גבי דקתני גבי נערה המאורסה Gabei diktani gabei naarah hameorasah
that it says over there by the betrothed maiden לאתויי leatuyei is
coming to include הלך אבי עם שלוחי הבעל halach avi im shluchei
habaal if the father's messengers accompanied the husband's messengers או שהלכו שלוחי
האב עם שלוחי o shehalchu shluchei haav im shluchei I'm sorry if
the father accompanied the husband's messengers... or the father's messengers, or the
father's messengers accompanied the husband's messengers. Okay, that's בנערה המאורסה benaarah hameorasah
and she's a נערה המאורסה naarah hameorasah so she has not yet
left the father's control because the father, even though she's going with
the husband's messengers, the father or his messengers are tagging along. In
that case, דאביה ובעלה מפירין נדריה de'aviah ubaalah mefirin nedareha that the
father she's still under the father's control and the father can still
annul the vows because it said זה הכלל כל שלא יצאה מרשות
האב אביה ובעלה מפירין נדריה. zeh haklal kol shelo yatzah mereshut ha'av
aviah ubaalah mefirin nedareha. As long as she hasn't left her father's
control, then the father can still annul. So what does that mean,
"as long as she hasn't"? Even in this case where you might
think she's already partially left, since she hasn't fully left her father's
control, the father is still in the picture. Okay, anytime you have
a זה הכלל zeh haklal like this, זה הכלל zeh haklal כל,
any case that, the implication is we're going to define that broadly,
right? Even if he's only barely hanging on to the father's barely
hanging on to his presence, she's still in the father's control and
he can still annul the vows. That's the זה הכלל zeh haklal
there. As long as she still to some degree is under the
father's control. Now, זה הכלל דתני גבי ואלו נערות, zeh haklal detani
gabei ve'elu naarot, זה הכלל zeh haklal that we have by our
פרק, perek, our פרק perek is called אלו נערות, Elu Naarot, right?
נערה המאורסה Naarah Hameorasah was the name of the פרק perek over
there in כתובות. Ketubot. It's interesting that it names the פרקים, prakim,
right? So this זה הכלל zeh haklal of our פרק perek of
אלו נערות, Elu Naarot, like look at דף ע', daf ayin, you
see where it says ואלו נדרים ve'elu nedarim at the top of
the page? Okay, so this זה הכלל zeh haklal of our פרק,
perek, which is as long as she does get into her own
control, then the vow is
established, ואתויי ve'atuyei comes to include מסר האב לשלוחי הבעל או שמסרו
שלוחי אב לשלוחי הבעל, masar ha'av lishluchei habaal o shemasru shluchei av
lishluchei habaal, so once she's handed over to the husband's messengers without
the father being present or his representatives being present, even though she
has not yet entered into her husband's house and her husband isn't
there yet, she's just on the way, but once the father steps
back, in that case, שאין הבעל מיפר בקודמין, she'ein habaal mefer bekodmin,
in that case the father is out of the picture and therefore
she's now the funny thing is that she's not exact it's not
exactly our משנה mishnah because she's not exactly ברשות עצמה. birshut atzmah.
Now she's ברשות birshut you know the whatever, the what do you
call it? The ארוס, arus, you know the betrothed. But you know,
but she's considered to be, but so yeah, so it's a little
bit funny how it reads it in our משנה. mishnah. Let me
just see the ר"ן. Ran.
It's still not clear how it's reading it that she was יצאה
לרשות עצמה. yatzah lereshut atzmah. Meaning, since she leaves her father's control,
it's a very funny read. It doesn't mean that she was ever
independent in this state, but it meant that since she left her
father's control,
then any vows that she's had until this point can no longer
be annulled because if you remember, a vow she had when she
was betrothed can only be annulled while she's still betrothed. As soon
as she's married, right? As soon as she has the נישואין, nisuin,
effectively this is like a type of a חופה, chuppah, then any
prior vows, even from the betrothal period, cannot be annulled by the
husband, right? Remember that? Right? So that's the way it's reading it.
כל שיצאה לרשות עצמה, kol sheyatzah lereshut atzmah, I don't get why
it's רשות עצמה. reshut atzmah. She's not יצאה לרשות, yatzah lereshut, she
was יוצאת מרשות האב. yotzet mereshut ha'av. She's but she's entering into
רשות הבעל. reshut habaal. But anyway, once she enters into רשות הבעל,
reshut habaal, even if she hasn't seen the guy and there hasn't
yet been a חופה, chuppah, she's just with the guy's messengers and
she's על הדרך al haderech and she's at the airport or whatever
it is, that she's there with her messengers, now she's left her
father's control, so any prior vows can now not be annulled. Okay,
it's not really פשט pshat of our משנה. mishnah. Yes?
But this husband would have had the opportunity, you're talking about prior
vows, he would have had the opportunity
until the time of נישואין. nisuin. Exactly. So that's how it's reading
the משנה, mishnah, but once she fully leaves the father's control, then
that opportunity is lost.
But what about prior vows? Right? So then he had it.
Yes, he had it, but they are still considered prior. The reason
he was able to do it before the נישואין nisuin was because
it was fundamentally the father that was doing it and from the
father's perspective they weren't prior. But once they have the נישואין, nisuin,
then it's only about his role and from his role, vows, you
know, those vows are considered to be prior. Okay. All right. So
that was like a little forced read of our משנה, mishnah, but
anyway, reminded us about this question about exactly where that threshold is,
where they cross the threshold. Okay. Now we have another fun little
riddle משנה mishnah which, not really a riddle, but basically what the
משנה's mishnah going to do, I'll just prepare you for it, is
take three cases and turn them into nine. Okay? Which and it's
really just distracting because there's three basic factors here and it just
you can make it nine because you can make irrelevant other pieces
of it. But and the and this is a משנה mishnah of
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda where the ירושלמי Yerushalmi basically says that רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda only taught this משנה mishnah לחדד בו את התלמידים.
lechahed bo et hatalmidim. Okay? To keep people on their toes. All
right. So basically let me tell you what the משנה's mishnah going
to say and then we'll read it, which is there are three
women, we're talking about a woman that's יצאה... yatzah... יצאה לרשות עצמה.
yatza lereshus atzma. Now she could be, how does a woman get
to be יצאה לרשות עצמה? yatza lereshus atzma? How does she get
to be her own woman? Right. So basically there are,
I mean one is, you know, married and divorced, right? So which
is the case of the תורה, Torah, or a widowed. But without
the case of the תורה, Torah, you could also have an independent
woman, which is number one is a בוגרת, bogeres, right? She, which
by the way I pointed out many times, it's not clear anywhere
in the תורה Torah that when a woman reaches any age of
adulthood she becomes her own woman, right? The תורה Torah always talks
about the father marrying off the girl to the, you know, to
the husband, never talks about an independent woman. You could say that,
you know, that's because of course they were all getting married off
very young, but this idea that there's an age in which she
becomes independent is something that, you know, the rabbis understand in terms
of the תורה Torah law. So number one is that she's a
בוגרת, bogeres, twelve and a half, or she's a יתומה, yesoma, she's
an orphan, the father dies, okay? So that makes her. Or what's
the third case?
Or,
let me, married and got divorced.
Or, yeah yeah, one minute, hold on, wait, I'm just wondering if
the divorce is in the משנה. Mishna. Yeah,
right, and that she got divorced, she got married and divorced, exactly.
Okay. So those are the, so those are the three cases in
the משנה. Mishna. Married and divorced, which is called, just to confuse
you, יתומה בחיי האב, yesoma bechayei ha'av, okay? Which is, I don't
know, because it means the father's alive, she's still, you know, somebody
who's a minor who should be considered to be under the father's
control, but because she's been married and divorced, she's considered to be
emancipated, okay? We would say an emancipated minor, okay? So anyway, an
adult, an emancipated minor, יתומה בחיי האב, yesoma bechayei ha'av, which is
not because by going to court but by getting divorced, right? And
a, and a real יתומה. yesoma. So what we're going to do
is we're just going to turn those into nine cases by mixing
and matching different, you know, different circumstances. So let's take a look.
I just thought that we looked at a different model with a
בת כהן, bas kohein, right? If she's, if she's got divorced, she
goes back to the father.
That's right, ושבה אל בית אביה כנעוריה, veshava el beis aviha kine'ureha,
exactly, very excellent point. So it's sort of like I guess there
what, that's a really good point, but there the way it would
be understood is like she's connected to the household but not under
the control of. But you're right, it still has that phrase of
בית אביה. beis aviha. You know, I don't know if that's פשט
pshat in, that difference is פשט pshat in the תורה, Torah, right?
That's a very good point. Okay, so
תשע נערות נדריהן קיימים. tesha ne'aros nidreihen kayamim. So nine young, nine
lasses, nine women, their vows are established. Now the first case is
going to be a בוגרת, bogeres, okay? Three variations of,
right, of בוגרת, bogeres, I think. I keep on getting confused which
one's coming first.
Okay, so anyway, let's take a look. בוגרת, bogeres, a woman who's
a בוגרת, bogeres, ויתומה, veyesoma, and she also happens to be, look
at that, some people get doubly lucky. She's independent two ways. You
know that terrible joke, right? What is it? It's that like somebody
says, "Oh, I hear your daughter got married to that doctor." He
says, "Yeah, but she got divorced." He says, "Oh, but then but
afterwards she got married to this other guy, he's a lawyer." "Oh,
so nice." "Yeah, but but then he died." He says, "But now
she's got married like whatever to
a, I don't know, what's another one? Let's, anyway, a
Wall Street guy." He says, "Yeah, but got divorced." He says, "So
basically you've got like a doctor, a lawyer, and a Wall Street,
all so, how lucky can you get?" Right? So, all
right, anyway, so here she gets lucky, anyway, she has, she's independent
in many different ways.
Once she's a בוגרת. bogeres.
I understand, that's why it's really three, because we're throwing in other
life circumstances that once you have the key one, becomes superfluous, okay?
So בוגרת, bogeres, she's a בוגרת, bogeres, ויתומה, veyesoma, she also happens
to be an
orphan. That's one case. Again, meaning בחיי האב. bechayei ha'av. Or נערה
ובגרה ויתומה. na'ara uvagra veyesoma. Okay, let's say she was a, she
made a vow when she was a נערה na'ara and then she
became a בוגרת bogeres and then you know and then the father,
and then, one minute, hold on, I've got to make sure that
I'm explaining this right. One minute, let me just double check the
רן Ran one second. So נערה ובגרה ויתומה בחיי האב. na'ara uvagra
veyesoma bechayei ha'av. Oh, yeah. So the רן Ran says the יתומה
yesoma here does not mean literally יתומה, yesoma, it means יתומה בחיי
האב, yesoma bechayei ha'av, just to confuse things, which means that she
got divorced. One
minute, let me just double check. Hold on.
Right, right, I'm sorry, because it's always confusing which is the key
one that each group is focusing on. So let's start this again.
The key one that this group is focusing on is actually the
יתומה, yesoma, and the יתומה yesoma right you wouldn't have thought about
that, and the יתומה yesoma actually here means יתומה בחיי האב, yesoma
bechayei ha'av, which basically means that she had been married and divorced.
Okay, so let's start this again. She's a בוגרת bogeres and a
יתומה. yesoma. That's one case. Again, meaning
בחיי האב. bechayei ha'av. Or Case number three
is נערה שלא בגרה והיא יתומה na'ara shelo bagra v'hi yitoma and
she is a woman who's been married and divorced. So basically, a
woman who's been married and divorced, whether she's a בוגרת bogeret or
whether she's not a בוגרת, bogeret, or whether she is a or
whether she was a started as a נערה na'ara and ended as
a בוגרת, bogera, that's really all three possibilities. Okay, if she basically
is a יתומה בחיי האב, yitoma b'chayei ha'av, then any vow she
makes at that, in that status, will be, you know, will be
nobody can annul them. Okay, that's one set of groups which is
all basically because she's been divorced. Okay, now group number two.
בוגרת ומת אביה. bogeret u'met aviha. No, so here it's about יתומה
בחיי האב. yitoma b'chayei ha'av.
No, no, I'm sorry, this is a real יתומה. yitoma. Okay, I
don't know why I keep on getting confused. Okay, בוגרת ומת אביה.
bogeret u'met aviha. Okay, so now here's about a real orphan, okay,
not a woman who is divorced, a real orphan. So she's a
בוגרת bogeret and her father has died. Okay, נערה ובוגרת ומת אביה,
na'ara u'bogera u'met aviha, or she made a vow when she was
a נערה na'ara now she's a בוגרת, bogera, but again the key
point being her father had
died. Or נערה שלא בגרה ומת אביה na'ara shelo bagra u'met aviha
in all those three cases. So again basically case number one was
a case of a woman divorced, it doesn't matter whether in that
case she was a בוגרת, bogera, a נערה, na'ara, or a נערה
na'ara who became a בוגרת. bogera. And here you have a woman
who is orphaned and also in that case it doesn't matter whether
in addition to being orphaned she was a נערה, na'ara, a בוגרת,
bogera, or a נערה na'ara who became a בוגרת. bogera. It's basically
about her being orphaned. Okay, that's group number two, and group number
three is about going to be about her being a בוגרת. bogera.
Okay. נערה שמת אביה ומשמת אביה בגרה, na'ara she'met aviha u'mishemet aviha
bagra, a woman who was a נערה na'ara then her father died
and then she became a בוגרת. bogera. Okay. Or בגרה bagra בוגרת
ואביה קיים bogeret v'aviha kayam or she's a בוגרת bogera and her
father is alive. Or נערה בוגרת ואביה קיים, na'ara bogeret v'aviha kayam,
she was a נערה na'ara and now she's a בוגרת bogera and
her father is alive. So basically you, before we had three scenarios:
נערה, na'ara, בוגרת, bogera, and נערה na'ara who became a בוגרת. bogera.
Since here the key is בוגרת bogera you can't have all you
can't have those three scenarios. You could only have two of them,
right, בוגרת bogera or a נערה na'ara who became a בוגרת. bogera.
But then what can vary is, is the father alive or is
the father dead?
You also had cases she married.
Yeah, although we didn't throw that in yet, you could have made
twenty-seven, that'll be a little exercise for you at home, Michael. Okay,
רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda anyway, bottom line is in all these cases
she made it either because she was a בוגרת, bogera, when she
was an orphan, or when she was a had been divorced. In
all these cases רבי יהודה אומר, Rebbe Yehuda omer, okay, אף המשיא
בתו af hamasi bito
now it's not clear because it sounds like the first position wasn't
רבי יהודה, Rebbe Yehuda, the גמרא's Gemara going to say it is,
and also it sounds like he's saying something new which he isn't,
but let's take a look. אף המשיא בתו הקטנה ונתאלמנה ונתגרשה, af
hamasi bito haktana v'nitalmana v'nitgarsha,
a man who marries off his minor daughter once she becomes an
אלמנה almana or a גרושה, gerusha, once she gets divorced וחזרה אצלו
v'chazra etzlo and she returns to him, עדיין היא נערה adayin hi
na'ara even if she's still a נערה na'ara and she's not yet
a בוגרת, bogera, since she has been divorced she is now considered
to be emancipated. That's a יתומה בחיי האב. yitoma b'chayei ha'av. So
really that's just illustrating, it's not adding a point, it's just illustrating
that יתומה yitoma phrase earlier, that there's a יתומה yitoma which literally
the father is dead and there's a case where the father is
alive but she's been married and divorced. And I want to by
the way emphasize that a key word here is משיא בתו, masi
bito, it has to be נישואין nisuin because you remember until נישואין,
nisuin, even after אירוסין, erusin, she's still under the father's control. So
if she becomes widowed or divorced from אירוסין erusin she's never left
the father's control. For her to become independent she needs real נישואין.
nisuin. Okay, so she had real נישואין nisuin even if she's still
a minor, once it's real נישואין nisuin it's got she's fully left
the father's control, then if the husband dies or divorces her she's
independent. Let's see the גמרא. Gemara.
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, זו דברי
רבי יהודה, zo divrei Rebbe Yehuda, these are the words of רבי
יהודה, Rebbe Yehuda, אבל חכמים אומרים שלש נערות נדריהן קיימים, aval chachamim
omrim shalosh naarot nidreihem kayamim, they make it simple and obviously there's
no debate here, they're just saying they don't make it so complicated.
בוגרת ויתומה ויתומה בחיי האב. bogeret v'yitoma v'yitoma b'chayei ha'av. Okay, a
woman who is a בוגרת, bogera, a woman who is literally an
orphan, and a woman who's an orphan when the father is alive
which means a woman who has had נישואין nisuin and is now
divorced. Okay, and if you want to take a look at the
ר"ן Ran he
says דהנך תלתא כיילי להו תשעה דמתניתין, d'hanach tlata kailu lehu tisha
d'masnisin, those three include the nine of the משנה, mishna, שאף רבי
יהודה לא אמר אלא לחדד את התלמידים, she'af Rebbe Yehuda lo amar
ella l'chaded et hatzamdim, וכדכתיב דבי מתניתין, u'kidechasiv d'vei masnisin, he quotes
Yerushalmi. Okay, that was a little, just a little puzzle. Let's take
a look now at the next משנה. mishna. Okay, we're just going
full steam ahead. קונם שאיני נהנית לאבא, konam she'eini nehenet l'abba, that's
actually משנה mishna is a little more complicated. ולאביך. u'l'avich. Okay, אבא,
abba, a vow that I will not, always the ל le is
always a little complicated, but of, of, it means me. Okay, so
a vow that I will not get any benefit from my father,
your
father, אם עושה אני
על פיך. im ose ani al picha. If I do anything, produce
anything for you to eat. Okay, so basically, it's like one or
the other. If basically the husband eats something that the wife produces,
then the vow is triggered, and she cannot benefit from her father
or father-in-law. Okay, if he doesn't eat anything, then the vow isn't
triggered, then the תנאי tnai isn't triggered, but he's in a state
where he can't eat from what his wife produces. So either one
of those states is problematic. If he triggers the vow, he eats
from what she does, then she can't benefit. Now what's the problem
if she can't benefit from the father and father-in-law? Well, that's עינוי
נפש. inuy nefesh. Okay, even though she says she can't benefit from
the world, but even if she just can't benefit from the father
and the father-in-law, that's עינוי נפש. inuy nefesh. So that's a vow
that women would take either or not. Yes, so this would have
to be like not רבי יוסי. Reb Yosi. Good catch. I know,
okay, good catch. Moving on. Okay, fine. But she can't benefit from
the father and father-in-law, that's עינוי נפש. inuy nefesh. If he avoids
the triggering the vow, then he can't benefit from her, and that's
דברים שבינו לבינה. devarim shebeino l'veina. So one way or another, the
package of this vow is going to either impact דברים שבינו לבינה
devarim shebeino l'veina or be עינוי נפש. inuy nefesh. And therefore even
before it's been triggered, it can be annulled. Because the question here
is: can you annul a vow before it has taken effect? Which
by the way is an interesting תנינו, taninu, right? We saw in
the previous משנה, Mishnah, according to רבי עקיבא Rebi Akiva you can.
I'm a נזירה nezirah after thirty days, right? He annuls it before
it takes effect, because by when it's going to take effect, they're
going to be divorced, right? Or right, remember that case? We just
did that. So from the previous משנה Mishnah you see that you
can annul a vow before it takes effect. But here what we
have to, so that's one thing that's implicit here that we already
saw in the previous משנה. Mishnah. But the other thing that you
see is that to define it as a type of vow that
can be annulled, you sort of look at like the package. And
here in the package, one way or another, at least at this
stage of the משנה, Mishnah, we'll get to the next stage of
the משנה, Mishnah, it'll be, it'll be those types of things that
give him the power to annul. Either the result of the package
here will be עינוי נפש inuy nefesh or the result will be
דברים שבינו לבינה. devarim shebeino l'veina. That's the first part of the
משנה. Mishnah. The second part is a bigger חידוש. chiddush. Here's the
second part. שאיני נהנה לך
אם עושה אני פי אבא ועל פי אביך.
she'eini nehene
lach im ose ani pi abba v'al pi avich. I won't get
any benefit from you, that's both דברים שבינו לבינה devarim shebeino l'veina
and עינוי נפש inuy nefesh if I, if your father, if my
father, your father benefit from anything that I do. Okay, now, in
that case, if the תנאי tnai is triggered, it's דברים שבינו לבינה,
devarim shebeino l'veina, עינוי נפש, inuy nefesh, he can annul it. But
why can't she just go through life not doing anything, like having
her father and father-in-law not benefit from her? That's not עינוי נפש,
inuy nefesh, right? And it's not דברים שבינו לבינה. devarim shebeino l'veina.
Everybody with me here? Okay, yes. Good question. She said, I won't
get any benefit from you. That's עינוי נפש inuy nefesh and בינו
לבינה beino l'veina if your father and my father ever benefit from
anything that I do. Okay, so if she just avoids triggering the
vow, so the fact that her father and his father can't benefit
from her, she's not suffering, that's not עינוי נפש, inuy nefesh, and
it's not בינו לבינה. beino l'veina. I understand,
so we had a previous משנה, Mishnah, if you remember, that said
that if basically he says things about his father, his brother, her
father, whatever, it's not בינו לבינה beino l'veina even though he indirectly
suffers or is upset because it doesn't directly impact בינו לבינה. beino
l'veina. So in this case, you would think he couldn't annul it.
Because how can I annul it? The vow won't, you know, maybe
the vow won't take effect. And maybe I, you know, maybe I'd
have to wait till it took effect until I could annul it.
Who knows? Okay, maybe then it would be too late, it wouldn't
be יום שמעו. yom shamo. Okay, so the way the ר"ן Ran
explains why he can annul it is because basically he says it's
like it's inevitable. That how are you going to go through your
life making sure that your father, your father-in-law, whatever, never benefit from
anything you do? And since, or maybe inevitably is putting it a
little bit strongly, but since it is so highly likely, we view
it as though it's already go, like as though we can anticipate
it'll take effect, it is בינו לבינה beino l'veina and therefore he
can annul it. Now, no, no, no, the, if the תנאי tnai
is triggered, the vow is בינו לבינה. beino l'veina. The vow is
also עינוי נפש. inuy nefesh. It's just that you could avoid having
the תנאי tnai triggered. Now what you could also say is, now
here, right, now here's what I would like to add, which is
given that we've seen before that you can really separate the annulling
from the effect, you could say after thirty days and you can
the husband can annul it today, you could say after a year,
whatever, the husband can annul it today. Maybe even if it was
completely a question whether it would take effect. You know, maybe she,
if she would say I don't know, if the Mets win the
World Series.
So, you know, who knows? Maybe it will take effect, maybe it
won't, but it doesn't matter. She made a vow, let. And therefore,
if it winds up that it took effect, he's done the annulling
on the day that he heard. Who says that we have to
know it will take effect in order for, right? Since if it
takes effect, it will be a דברים שבינו לבינה devarim shebeino l'veina
and it will be an עינוי נפש, inui nefesh, so who needs,
you know, to care about whether it definitely will be or or
not. Anyway, so I think that's a question to raise, but the
ר"ן Ran says that the reason he can annul it is because
we can anticipate that it will take effect. Now I will say
Michael, that the רא"ש Rosh and other ראשונים Rishonim try to say
that it's not what you were saying, but it is a problem
because of that earlier משנה mishna about אביך avicha and so on.
But they try to say that here, the package is something that's
בינו לבינה. beino l'veina. Meaning the fact that, meaning if she had
just said
"I'm not going my father, your father can't benefit from me," okay,
he's indirectly annoyed at that, but it doesn't have to do directly
with their relationship. He can't annul it. But here if she says,
"your father can't can't, what is it? Can't, if your father benefits
from me, I can't get benefit from you," so that somehow the
combination of those two make it דברים שבינו לבינה. devarim shebeino l'veina.
Like the fact that like you know, I don't want, I'm trying
to think this one through, you're going to avoid benefiting my father
so that the vow isn't triggered, right? But the triggering of the
vow is a דברים שבינו לבינה, devarim shebeino l'veina, so it sort
of like packages the whole thing as a דברים שבינו לבינה, devarim
shebeino l'veina, right? If it was just "I'm not going to give
any benefit to your father," okay, I'm I'm annoyed, but it's not
there's nothing directly that gets to the relationship of the two of
us. But here that it's a תנאי tenai that's connected to a
vow that is about the two of us puts the whole thing
into a בינו לבינה beino l'veina type of a package. Okay, so
that's the way some other ראשונים Rishonim want to read it. But
one way or the other, okay, either the whole package is בינו
לבינה beino l'veina or the actual, even if the trigger is not,
the effect of the vow is בינו לבינה beino l'veina and that's
enough for him to annul. So let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara.
Yeah, if her grandfather's safe for the having the grandchildren, is that
considered a benefit?
Because that would also be kind of the inevitable.
Right, so that gets into that whole interesting point, that gets into
that whole interesting פרק perek before about what's considered הנאה, hana'ah, right?
I mean, and how much are we talking about a concrete object?
And like remember the גמרא Gemara talked about like cutting through somebody's
yard and other types of things? So, yeah, now I'd have to
go back and try to remember all of that and then try
to fit it into this, so I don't know, but that would
be, I mean I think that would be a real question, you
know, because how concrete of a הנאה hana'ah is that? Okay, תניא,
tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braita, "שאיני נהנית לאבא ולאביך אם
אני עושה לפיך," she'eini nehenet l'abba u'l'avicha im ani osa l'ficha, I
won't get benefit from my father, your father, if you get benefit
from me, so that's like the first case in the משנה, mishna,
right? So her not getting benefit from the father is is עינוי
נפש, inui nefesh, and not doing for the husband is בינו לבינה.
beino l'veina. One is the תנאי, tenai, one is the trigger. רבי
נתן אומר לא יפר, Rabbi Natan omer lo yafer, he can't be
מיפר, meifer, even though the whole thing is a type of a
you know, one way or the other, it's the type of things
that he has power over, he can't be מיפר. meifer. We'll see
why in a minute. וחכמים אומרים יפר, v'Chachamim omrim yafer, and the
חכמים Chachamim say he can be מיפר. meifer. Now that's our משנה.
mishna. Now, but רבי נתן Rabbi Natan is interesting and we're going
to have the next statement will make רבי נתן Rabbi Natan even
in sharper relief, so let's read the next statement. "מנועה אני מן
היהודים," menu'ah ani min haYehudim, I cannot get any sex from anybody,
any Jews, have any sex with them,
"אם משמשתך," im meshameshetcha, if I have sex with you. Okay? So
one way or the other way, basically the nature of the vow
is עינוי נפש, inui nefesh, okay,
so we said these things automatically exclude the husband.
Well, yes, well, okay, that's true, but we said before also that
since she already can't have sex with anybody else, that therefore clearly
this does include the husband because there's no purpose of her making
the vow about anybody else. Okay, remember we said that before? So
it means everybody else including the husband, every everybody not else, everybody
including the husband. Because if it was just everybody else...
Okay, so what's the תנאי? tenai? The תנאי tenai is if I
have sex with you now, I can never have sex with you
later.
Exactly. Right, exactly. If we, right, if we have sex once, then
I'm forbidden to have sex from you from that point on.
But then isn't it automatically בטל, batel, because that's against the...?
You know, you do it in one of these
ways, "הנאת תשמישך עלי," hana'at tashmishcha alai, whatever, you know. She's saying
הנאת תשמיש hana'at tashmish of other people are of all the הנאה
hana'ah of the תשמיש tashmish of all other men are forbidden to
me, of all men including you, is forbidden to me. So that
she can do, she's not directly saying she won't have sex, she's
saying they're forbidden, if I have sex with you, that's just a
תנאי. tenai. Okay, so one way or the other,
basically she's not going to be able to have sex with her
husband, or she'll have sex once and then no more, okay? Or
she just won't ever have sex and never trigger the תנאי. tenai.
So that's clearly עינוי נפש inui nefesh and well, actually sadly the
גמרא Gemara has a question whether sex is עינוי נפש, inui nefesh,
but anyway, it's clearly בינו לבינה, beino l'veina, okay? And they're all
in the same פרשה, parsha, it all boils down to her having
sex with the husband. So you would think that everybody should say
that's basically one, you know, a simple vow that he should be
able to annul. Comes along רבי נתן Rabbi Natan and says, רבי
נתן אומר... Rabbi Natan omer... רבי נתן אומר לא יפר וחכמים אומרים
יפר.
Rebbi Nosson omer lo
yofer vechachamim omrim yofer. Now, what is the problem with רבי נתן?
Rebbi Nosson? So take a look at the ר"ן, Ran, and the
ר"ן Ran says that רבי נתן's Rebbi Nosson's position is, let's take
a look.
So it's like five lines from the bottom, middle of the line.
וסלקא דעתך V'salka daitach says the ר"ן, Ran, אמינא, Amina, דאפילו רבי
נתן מודה בכי האי גוונא, D'afilu Rebbi Nosson modeh b'chi hai gavna,
even רבי נתן Rebbi Nosson should agree to that case, דיפר, D'yafer,
דחל הנדר D'chal haneder מעיקרא, Me'ikara, that it's like the נדר neder
took effect and it's all basically about a נדר neder about sex.
So קמשמע לן Kamashma lan דאפילו הכי כיון דלא חל ממש לא
יפר. D'afilu hachi kivan d'lo chal mamash lo yofer. Even though the
effect of the נדר neder effectively means starting right now they're not
having sex or whatever the host-sex wants, but nevertheless רבי נתן Rebbi
Nosson says you cannot be מיפר meifer until the נדר neder takes
effect. So it's interesting that that's not being brought into conversation with
the previous, right? Because that seems like very much like רבי ישמעאל's
Rebbi Yishmael's point, right? That רבי ישמעאל... Rebbi Yishmael... now even רבי
ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael by the way didn't say that you have to
wait for it to take effect to annul it. He said if
it taking effect is at a different stage then that determines who
has the power. But let's say she said לאחר שלשים יום, L'achar
shloshim yom, they stayed married the whole time, when would רבי ישמעאל
Rebbi Yishmael say you should do the annulment? He might be okay
to say in that case you can go ahead and do the
annulment at the original time, right? So it's very interesting. It was
רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva certainly said you could do it earlier, רבי
ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael might have been able to say you could do
it earlier, but here we're having a position of רבי נתן Rebbi
Nosson that at least the ר"ן Ran is explaining, only makes it
is, and the גמרא's Gemara's going to, not just the ר"ן, Ran,
the גמרא's Gemara's going to say it more explicitly, רבי נתן Rebbi
Nosson says no annulling until the נדר neder takes effect.
Why wasn't he like earlier in this discussion?
I don't know, that's what I'm saying.
No, מנא? Mena?
תשמיש? Tashmish? Yeah, I don't know. So let's take a look. דברי
תורה עניים במקום אחד ועשירים במקום אחר. Divrei Torah aniyim b'makom echad
v'ashirim b'makom acher. Let's take a look now the גמרא Gemara has
a nice story. Okay.
ההוא גברא, Hahu gavra, there was a man דאסר הנאה דעלמא עליה,
D'asar hana'at d'alma alei, he made the הנאה hana'ah of the world
forbidden to him, go he tried to go through life not getting
any הנאה hana'ah from the world.
Okay. אי נסיב איתתא, Ei nasiv iteta, if he got married עד
דלא תנינא הלכתא Ad d'lo tanina hilcheta before he had had a
chance to learn הלכה. halacha. Meaning to go ahead and, you know,
תנינא הלכתא tanina hilcheta is more like as opposed to like really
learn ש"ס, Shas, like all the שקלא וטריא shakla v'tarya and whatever
of the גמרא, Gemara, it's more like, you know, learning like the
ממרא's, memra's, learning the, you know, משניות, mishnayot,
פסק הלכה, psak halacha, whatever. But he wanted to spend a certain
amount of time sitting in ישיבה yeshiva and learning before he got
married before he got married.
So he figured the way he's going to spur himself to do
this, this is why people take vows sometimes, to force themselves to
do something they want to do and they don't feel that they'll
have the strength of their convictions to see it through, is he
basically said if I ever give in and get married before I've
had a chance to really spend a few good years learning at
ישיבה, yeshiva, then the whole הנאה hana'ah of the world would be
forbidden to me. Now, what happened? Okay.
Now, but he tried,
okay. רהט באגפי ותובלי. Rehat b'agpei v'tuvlei. He ran with a אגפי
agpei and תובלי. tuvlei. Now what that means the ר"ן Ran sort
of says it means like his staff and
his like flask, others like this pseudo רש"י Rashi says it means
a ladder and a rope, which means like up and down, he
ran like, you know, all over the world, he, you know, he
drove, he used like he tried as hard as possible. It's an
idiom to mean he tried as hard as he could, he ran
with a ladder and a pulley and whatever. ולא אמצי למתני V'lo
amtzei l'mitni and he wasn't able to to be able to to
learn, I mean because anyway he meant to say I'm going to...
yeah, I don't know, he couldn't find a רבי Rebbi to teach
him. I mean he didn't just say I'm going to spend X
number of years in ישיבה, yeshiva, he said I'm going to actually
accomplish a certain goal, right? So he tried as hard as he
could but anyway he couldn't find a ישיבה, yeshiva, he couldn't find
a רבי, Rebbi, he wasn't able to understand what he was learning,
he didn't succeed. Okay. So now and now he's sitting around not
getting married. Okay. So what happened? So אתא רב אחא בר רב
הונא ושבשי'. Ata Rav Acha bar Rav Huna v'shabshei. So רב הונא...
Rav Huna... רב אחא בר רב הונא Rav Acha bar Rav Huna
came and
he basically misled him, like, you know, he misled him. Okay. If
you take a look at the side it says פיתהו. piteihu. He
seduced him. But anyway he misled him. He intentionally misled him. And
he said it's not a problem, you tried hard, you know, you
gave it your best effort, so you satisfied your vow, don't worry,
go get married. And that wasn't true because his vow wasn't I
would try. Although one could wonder how much does this fit in,
remember we had a whole discussion earlier about whether like, you know,
whether it was like יש אונס או אין אונס, yesh ones o
ein ones, right? About how much to by how much when you
take a vow do you mean you're going to try as hard
as you possibly as you can, and how much do you mean
you're really going to do it and so on. But anyway it
sounds like the assumption was that actually he didn't satisfy his vow
even though but he told him yeah yeah it's fine, you tried
hard enough, you satisfied your vow. ונסיב איתתא, V'nasiv iteta, and he
married a woman.
Okay then ודשדי קטינא. V'dshadi katina. Now he put mud on him.
Now who put mud on who for what purpose? So the ר"ן
Ran says that what it means was was that whoever this was
that misled him. him רב אחא בר רב הונא Rav Aha bar
Rav Huna like threw some blood on his garments and then said,
"Oh my god, I got my blood—not blood, whatever, dirt—I got mud
on my garments, I gotta go to a—to a—to the dry cleaners.
Oh wait, I can't go to dry cleaners. I can't get הנאה
hana'ah from anyone. I don't know how I can get married if
I can't get הנאה hana'ah from anyone." Okay, but anyway, he did
something to make him realize that he had to go be מתיר
matir his נדר. neder. Now, of course, I don't know, he was
told that he didn't have to worry about his נדר; neder; whether
exactly clear how throwing dirt on him is going to make him
realize he has to מתיר matir his נדר. neder. But anyway, you
know, the רש"י Rashi said that it basically means he put tar
on his face so he wouldn't be recognized and get back to
the נדר. neder. Yeah, it's like, but it's not clear why he
has to. Anyway, let's take a look.
So whatever that means, maybe he started having like second thoughts about
this.
Well, okay, let's take a look what happens. So I'm not exactly—well,
we'll read the rest of the story and you can go back
and you can tell me why you think he put the tar
on the face. Okay, ואתא לקמיה דרב
חסדא, va-ata le-kamei de-Rav Hisda,
and he came in front of רב חסדא Rav Hisda and he
said, "Look, here's the story. I went ahead and I married. I
tried as hard as possible, I couldn't—I couldn't learn. I got married,
and now I'm afraid that my נדר neder actually has taken effect
and I need you to—and I need to be annulled from the
vow." Okay, so אמר רבא, Amar Rava, "מאן חכים למעבד כי האי
מילתא אי לאו רב אחא בר רב הונא." man hakim le-mevad ki
hai milta i lav Rav Aha bar Rav Huna. Ah,
nobody would have been smart enough to figure out how to do
this, you know, mislead this guy, and that that would be a
good way of going about this, except רב אחא בר רב הונא.
Rav Aha bar Rav Huna. Why was that a smart thing to
do? דגברא רבא הוא, de-gavra raba hu, he's a great תלמיד חכם,
tamid chacham, דקסבר, de-kasavar, and he thinks כי היכי דפליגי רבנן ורבי
נתן בהפרה, ki heichi de-paligi rabanan ve-Rabbi Natan be-hafara, the same way
the רבנן rabanan and רבי נתן Rabbi Natan debate by הפרה hafara
whether it has to take effect or not, הכא נמי פליגי בשאלה,
hacha nami paligi bi-she'eila, they debate by going to a חכם hacham
to מתיר matir the נדר. neder. And רבי נתן Rabbi Natan might
say the same way you can't do an annulling until it takes
effect, you can't do a releasing of the vow until it takes
effect. And he wanted to take, you know, to be—to satisfy the
position of רבי נתן. Rabbi Natan. Now, in the end, we rule
like the חכמים hachamim anyway, but nevertheless, he made two assumptions: number
one is רבי נתן Rabbi Natan would say even when it comes
to releasing from a vow, it has to take effect; and number
two is I want to play it safe according to רבי נתן.
Rabbi Natan. And that's why rather than releasing the guy from his
vow back here when he—after he had tried really hard—he made it
that the guy would actually trigger the vow, and now he would
be able—and now he felt more comfortable releasing him from it. I
don't know, to ask me it seems like you're playing with, like,
you know, with some, like, you know, sort of like loaded ammunition
here, because as soon as he gets married, then as soon as
he benefit—gets some benefit from somebody in the world—he's transgressed. Now, it
is true once you release him retroactively he won't have transgressed, but
still it's like why not just take care of it back there?
But anyway, רבא Rava was impressed. Okay, ah, he tricked him into
triggering it and now we can release him from his vow even
according to רבי נתן Rabbi Natan because the vow has taken effect.
I still don't get what the plaster was about.
So—so I think maybe he put the plaster because he was embarrassed
because he got a release from this guy
and now he felt he had to ask again. Maybe. Right, that
could be, that could be, yeah, that could be. Okay, let's just
read a little bit more because we have to get more than
two דף daf ahead. Okay, דכתיב, de-ketiv, now רב פפא
אמר, Rav Papa amar,
רב פפא Rav Papa says, "מחלוקת בהפרה." mahloket be-hafara. No, no, no,
the whole debate about whether it has to take effect is only
by הפרה. hafara. דרבי נתן סבר אינה בעל מיפר אלא אם כן
חל הנדר, de-Rabbi Natan savar eina ba'al meifer ela im kein hal
ha-neder, רבי נתן Rabbi Natan says it has to take effect before
it's annulled. דכתיב—and de-ketiv where does he get that from? The following
verse: וחפרה הלבנה—"and ve-hafrah ha-levanah these the moon will be embarrassed." Now,
what does that have to do with anything? So it seems to
be a play on words. What word does וחפרה ve-hafrah look a
lot like?
Almost like הפרה. hafara.
Okay, הפרה hafara with a ח. het. Okay, הפרה hafara and הלבנה.
ha-levanah. If the ח het of the וחפרה ve-hafrah could be a
ה, hei, then the ה hei of the הלבנה ha-levanah could be
a
ח. het. So והפרה חל ve-hafara hal instead of הלבנה, ha-levanah, תחל.
t-hal. And then somehow בנה banah means a נדר neder because it
means a
במה. bamah. וכל הנודר כאילו בונה במה. ve-chol ha-nodeir ke-ilu boneh bamah.
So הפרה hafara is when חל hal the במה. bamah.
Okay, רבנן סברי, rabanan savri, and the רבנן rabanan hold בעל מיפר
אף על פי שלא חל הנדר, ba'al meifer af al pi she-lo
hal ha-neder, the husband can do it even before it took effect.
דכתיב, de-ketiv, מפר מחשבות ערומים—God meifer mahshavot arumim annuls the schemes of
the devious—so you can annul something even when it's just a thought,
a מחשבה, mahshavah, before it's taken effect. Okay, so they have this
debate when it's a הפרה. hafara. אבל בשאלה, aval bi-she'eila, when it
comes to undoing it, דברי הכל אין
חכם מתיר כלום אלא אם כן חל הנדר. divrei ha-kol ein hacham
matir klum ela im kein hal ha-neder. Everybody agrees it has to
take effect before the חכם hacham can do it. So what he
did was getting him to trigger wasn't just to be יוצא yotzei
רבי נתן, Rabbi Natan, he got him to trigger because he really
felt that by התרת נדרים hataras nedarim it needs to take effect
according to everyone. Why should התרת נדרים hataras nedarim be different? דכתיב,
de-ketiv, לא יחל דברו. lo yahel devaro. This verse, "He cannot violate
his word," which from where we learn he can't violate his word
but other
people. But somehow
the word יחל yachel also has the word what in it?
חל, chal, right? The whole thing's with a חל. chal. So the
ability to be יחל דברו yachel devaro also requires חל דברו, chal
devaro, only after it's taken effect. Now logically, that's hard to understand,
right? Because since the way the חכם chacham does it is by
saying you never really you wouldn't have wanted to do it and
retroactively it's all בטעות, b'taos, who needs it to take effect in
order to identify it as having been בטעות, b'taos, right? But nevertheless
there still is a formal process of התרת נדרים hataras nedarim and
according to this everybody requires it takes effect and that's why he
tricked this guy because in order to do התרת נדרים hataras nedarim
he felt that נדר neder had to take effect. Okay this discussion
is not over, we will continue with this tomorrow. סימן
קח?
Siman
Kuf-Ches?
Unless we wind up what's it going to be if we wind
up finishing tomorrow? I don't know. Okay anyway.
We'll save the last line for Friday and we'll just have a
party
before starting on Monday.